Illinois Central Gulf Railroad Company Selected Personnel Files 5295
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- Series 2: Subject Files, 1901-1969
  - Wage matters - orders and unions of railway employees [folder 2 of 2], 1936-1940 (Box 16, Folder 3b)
  - Wage matters - orders and unions of railway employees, 1943-1944 (Box 16, Folder 3c)
  - War Veterans - Interviews, 1946 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    Brief reports on the service history of all ICRR employees who served in WW2
  - War Veterans - Interviews [folder 1 of 3], 1946-1947 (Box 16, Folder 5a)
    Brief reports on the service history of all ICRR employees who served in WW2 (This folder includes a letter announcing a memorial to the 220 ICRR employees who died in the armed services during WW2.)
  - War Veterans - Interviews [folder 2 of 3], 1946 (Box 16, Folder 5b)
  - War Veterans - Interviews [folder 3 of 3], 1946 (Box 16, Folder 5c)
  - War Veterans - Re-enlistment, job security, seniority protections, G.I. Bill, etc., 1944-1948 (Box 16, Folder 6a)
  - War Veterans - Reclassification - Selective Service designations, 1943-1946 (Box 16, Folder 6b)
  - War Veterans - Interviews and Correspondence, 1946-1947 (Box 16, Folder 7a)
    Brief reports on the service history of all ICRR employees who served in WW2 and correspondence re returning service members' employment
  - War Veterans - Files and Correspondence [folder 1 of 2], 1942-1947 (Box 16, Folder 7b)
    Rosters of ICRR employees in service, casualty reports, re-employment of veterans, seniority rights of veterans
  - War Veterans - Files and Correspondence [folder 2 of 2], 1942-1947 (Box 16, Folder 7c)
  - Wartime Manpower - Preparation of Replacement Schedules No. I [folder 1 of 2], 1943-1944 (Box 17, Folder 1a)
    Selective Service Regulations
  - Wartime Manpower - Preparation of Replacement Schedules No. I [folder 2 of 2], 1943-1944 (Box 17, Folder 1b)
  - Wartime Manpower - Preparation of Replacement Schedules No. II [folder 1 of 2], 1943-1944 (Box 17, Folder 2a)
  - Wartime Manpower - Preparation of Replacement Schedules No. II [folder 2 of 2], 1943-1944 (Box 17, Folder 2b)
  - Wartime Manpower - Replacement Schedules [folder 1 of 2], 1943-1945 (Box 17, Folder 3a)
  - Wartime Manpower - Replacement Schedules [folder 2 of 2], 1943-1945 (Box 17, Folder 3b)
  - Wartime Manpower - Draft Act [folder 1 of 2], 1942-1943 (Box 17, Folder 4a)
    Railroads requesting deferments of certain classes of railroad employee
  - Wartime Manpower - Draft Act [folder 2 of 2], 1942-1943 (Box 17, Folder 4b)
  - Wartime Manpower - Deferments, 1942-1952 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    Obtaining release of men from the armed services
  - Wartime Manpower - Deferments [folder 1 of 3], 1945 (Box 17, Folder 6a)
    List submitted to Office of Defense Transportation and subsequent correspondence
  - Wartime Manpower - Deferments [folder 2 of 3], 1945 (Box 17, Folder 6b)
  - Wartime Manpower - Deferments [folder 3 of 3], 1945 (Box 17, Folder 6c)
  - Wartime Manpower - Regulations, 1943 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Western Association of Railway Executives - docket, 1942 (Box 17, Folder 8a)
  - Western Union and Postal Telegraph - curtailment of use, 1941-1943 (Box 17, Folder 8b)
  - Working Conditions, 1940 (Box 17, Folder 9)
    Letter to operating department employees covering better understanding re working conditions and the disagreements resulting therefrom
- Series 3: Interpretation of Rules, 1911-1935
  This series consists of a general index and thirteen volumes of Rulings and Interpretations on Shop Craft Rules, as were agreed on in 1935. In these volumes, the work rules and agreements between the ICRR and all non-operating shop-craft employees and their unions are filed along with correspondence, interpretations, rule applications, any minutes of meetings held regarding that rule, any subsequent interpretations, as well as charts and graphs containing quantitative data regarding the work rules. The unions involved in these agreements include: International Association of Machinists; International Brotherhood of Blacksmiths; International Brotherhood of Boilermakers; International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers; International Association of Railway Carmen; International Brotherhood of Sheetmetal Workers; and Brotherhood of Railway and Steamship Clerks. Many of the documents used in these volumes are duplicates of records found in the Subject Files, though these are marked "Reader Copy."
  - General Index to Rulings and Interpretations on Shop Craft Rules, 1935 (Box 17A, Folder 1)
    Subsequent to April 1, 1935 (sections A through I, Inc. )
  - Book #1 of Rulings and Interpretations on Shop Craft Rules, 1 to 12 Inc., 1923-1935 (Box 17A, Folder 2a)
    "Letters in each section of this book are in date order."
  - Book #2 of Rulings and Interpretations on Shop Craft Rules, 13 to 19 Inc., 1925-1935 (Box 17A, Folder 2b)
  - Book #3 of Rulings and Interpretations on Shop Craft Rules, 20-23 Inc. [folder 1 of 2], 1927-1935 (Box 17A, Folder 3a)
  - Book #3 of Rulings and Interpretations on Shop Craft Rules, 20-23 Inc. [folder 2 of 2], 1927-1935 (Box 17A, Folder 3b)
  - Book #4 of Rulings and Interpretations on Shop Craft Rules 24-27 Inc. [folder 1 of 2], 1926-1935 (Box 17A, Folder 4a)
  - Book #4 of Rulings and Interpretations on Shop Craft Rules 24-27 Inc. [folder 2 of 2], 1926-1935 (Box 17A, Folder 4b)
  - Book #5 of Rulings and Interpretations on Shop Craft Rules 28-35 Inc., 1923-1935 (Box 17A, Folder 5)
  - Book #6 of Rulings and Interpretations on Shop Craft Rules 36-49 Inc. [folder 1 of 2], 1920-1935 (Box 17A, Folder 6a)
  - Book #6 of Rulings and Interpretations on Shop Craft Rules 36-49 Inc. [folder 2 of 2], 1920-1935 (Box 17A, Folder 6b)
  - Book #7 of Rulings and Interpretations on Shop Craft Rules on Special Rules [folder 1 of 3], 1924-1935 (Box 17A, Folder 7a)
    Machinists - 50 to 64 Inc. "Letters in each section of this book are in date order."
  - Book #7 of Rulings and Interpretations on Shop Craft Rules on Special Rules [folder 2 of 3], 1928-1935 (Box 17A, Folder 7b)
    Boilermakers - 50 to 78 Inc. "Letters in each section of this book are in date order."
  - Book #7 of Rulings and Interpretations on Shop Craft Rules on Special Rules [folder 3 of 3], 1928-1935 (Box 17A, Folder 7c)
    Blacksmiths - 50 to 64 Inc. "Letters in each section of this book are in date order."
  - Book #8 of Rulings and Interpretations on Special Rules [folder 1 of 2], 1920-1935 (Box 17A, Folder 8a)
    Sheetmetal Workers, 50 to 61 Inc. Electricians, 50 to 64 Inc. "Letters in each section of this book are in date order."
  - Book #8 of Rulings and Interpretations on Special Rules [folder 2 of 2], 1924-1935 (Box 17A, Folder 8b)
    Carmen, 50 to 73 Inc. "Letters in each section of this book are in date order."
  - Book #9 of Rulings and Interpretations on General Shop Craft Cases, Sections A to H, Inc. [folder 1 of 2], 1911-1935 (Box 17A, Folder 9a)
  - Book #9 of Rulings and Interpretations on General Shop Craft Cases, Sections A to H, Inc. [folder 2 of 2], 1911-1935 (Box 17A, Folder 9b)
  - Book #10 of Rulings and Interpretations on General Shop Craft Subjects, Sections I - L Inc., 1923-1935 (Box 17A, Folder 10)
  - Book #11 of Rulings and Interpretations on General Shop Craft Cases, Sections M to N Inc., 1923-1935 (Box 17A, Folder 11)
  - Book #12 Rulings and Interpretations on General Shop Craft Cases, Sections O to Z Inc., 1922-1935 (Box 17A, Folder 12)
  - Book #13 Rulings and Interpretations on General Shop Craft Cases, Sections AA to KK, 1932-1935 (Box 17A, Folder 13)
- Series 4: Railroad Case Files, Arbitrations, and supporting materials, 1930-1971
  This series contain the files documenting some of the legal disputes between the ICRR and the railroad unions. The files contain correspondence, transcripts, legal filings, biographies of various emergency board members, the results of studies conducted in attempts to support various claims by the carrier, awards, and documentation on the results the awards by various boards had on the ICRR.
  Of note are the files documenting the hearings before the Interstate Commerce Commission in 1971 in which the ICC claimed jurisdiction over enforcing Equal Employment Opportunity in surface transportation, including the carriers.
  The C. T. Earle vs. ICRR Co. files contain the records regarding a suit brought by a switchman, with the support of the Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen, against the ICRR alleging that his seniority rights had been violated. This case became a test case for the ICRR, and twenty-three other similar suits are also documented in this file. One of the cases is also documented in the discrimination files in Series 2.
  The remainder of cases are concerned with the issues of crew consist, i.e. how many men it takes to operate a railroad. The dispute between the unions, who did not want any positions to be eliminated, and the carriers, who argued that the crew consists were outdated and not reflective of modern railroad practices, eventually culminated in the need for Emergency Board 172's intervention. A brief summary of the labor disputes leading up to the creation of this board may be found in the Affidavit of James E. Wolfe. As part of preparing for the hearing in front of this board, the ICRR employed a University of Chicago professor, Dr. Benjamin King, to design a Crew Consist Time and Motion Study. The study was functionally executed by John Roberts and other ICRR employees. The results of this study, as well as charts, IBM printouts, and graphs containing all of the raw data gathered..
  - Member of Emergency and Arbitration Boards - Biographical sketches of members only, 1956 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Special Board of Adjustment No. 170, Awards 1 to 66, 1957-1958 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    Clerks' cases withdrawn from the Third Division of the National Railroad Adjustment Boards for handling by Special Board of Adjustment No. 170.
  - Special Board of Adjustment No. 170, Award No.s 2 and 51, 1954-1958 (Box 18, Folder 3)
    with supporting documentation from the Clerks and the carrier
  - Before the Interstate Commerce Commission, Ex Parte No. 278, Equal Opportunity in Surface Transportation [folder 1 of 4], 1971 (Box 18, Folder 4a)
  - Before the Interstate Commerce Commission, Ex Parte No. 278, Equal Opportunity in Surface Transportation [folder 2 of 4], 1971 (Box 18, Folder 4b)
  - Before the Interstate Commerce Commission, Ex Parte No. 278, Equal Opportunity in Surface Transportation [folder 3 of 4], 1971 (Box 18, Folder 4c)
  - Before the Interstate Commerce Commission, Ex Parte No. 278, Equal Opportunity in Surface Transportation [folder 4 of 4], 1971 (Box 18, Folder 4d)
  - C.T. Earle vs. ICRR Co. [folder 1 of 6], 1934-1943 (Box 18, Folder 5a)
    Lawsuit filed by switchman, C. T. Earle, member of the BRT, against the ICRR for wrongful termination. The case is primarily about seniority rights. 23 other cases similar to this one were also affected by the final ruling, which found in favor of the ICRR. (Includes case file of George Clayborne, see box 8, folder 21b).
  - C.T. Earle vs. ICRR Co. [folder 2 of 6], 1934-1943 (Box 18, Folder 5b)
  - C.T. Earle vs. ICRR Co. [folder 3 of 6], 1934-1943 (Box 18, Folder 5c)
  - C.T. Earle vs. ICRR Co. [folder 4 of 6], 1934-1943 (Box 18, Folder 5d)
  - C.T. Earle vs. ICRR Co. [folder 5 of 6], 1934-1943 (Box 18, Folder 5e)
  - C.T. Earle vs. ICRR Co. [folder 6 of 6], 1934-1943 (Box 18, Folder 5f)
  - ORC, BRT vs. ICRR [folder 1 of 6], 1933 (Box 18, Folder 6a)
    Transcript of Proceedings of the Arbitration Board, volumes 1 to 6 and Award (missing volume 2).
  - ORC, BRT vs. ICRR [folder 2 of 6], 1933 (Box 18, Folder 6b)
  - ORC, BRT vs. ICRR [folder 3 of 6], 1933 (Box 18, Folder 6c)
  - ORC, BRT vs. ICRR [folder 4 of 6], 1933 (Box 18, Folder 6d)
  - ORC, BRT vs. ICRR [folder 5 of 6], 1933 (Box 18, Folder 6e)
  - ORC, BRT vs. ICRR [folder 6 of 6], 1933 (Box 18, Folder 6f)
  - Correspondence file re ORC, BRT vs. ICRR [folder 1 of 2], 1930-1938 (Box 18, Folder 7a)
  - Correspondence file re ORC, BRT vs. ICRR [folder 2 of 2], 1930-1938 (Box 18, Folder 7b)
  - Affidavit of James E. Wolfe, On behalf of Illinois Central Railroad Co., 1969 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    In the U.S. District Court for the Middle District of Tennessee, Nashville Division, Civil Action No. 5378
  - Emergency Board No. 172, BRT vs. ICRR in re Crew Consist, Report to President, 1968 (Box 19, Folder 2a)
  - Emergency Board No. 172, BRT vs. ICRR in re Crew Consist, Guideline Evidence on Crew Size, 1968 (Box 19, Folder 2b)
  - Emergency Board No. 172, BRT vs. ICRR in re Crew Consist, Crew Dispute Work Burden Evidence, 1967-1969 (Box 19, Folder 2c)
  - Emergency Board No. 172, BRT vs. ICRR in re Crew Consist, IC Crew Size Dispute, 1967-1969 (Box 19, Folder 2d)
  - Emergency Board No. 172, BRT vs. ICRR in re Crew Consist, IC Crew Size Dispute, 1967-1969 (Box 19, Folder 2e)
  - Emergency Board No. 172, BRT vs. ICRR in re Crew Consist, Financial Data, 1967-1969 (Box 19, Folder 2f)
  - Emergency Board No. 172, BRT vs. ICRR in re Crew Consist, NORC Poll in Crew Size Dispute, 1968-1969 (Box 19, Folder 2g)
  - Emergency Board No. 172, BRT vs. ICRR in re Crew Consist, Results of Time and Motion Study and Additional Information, 1967-1969 (Box 19, Folder 2h)
  - Emergency Board No. 172, BRT vs. ICRR in re Crew Consist, Time and Motion Study (Procedures), 1967-1969 (Box 19, Folder 2i)
  - Emergency Board No. 172, BRT vs. ICRR in re Crew Consist, Time and Motion Study (Procedures), 1967-1969 (Box 19, Folder 2j)
  - Emergency Board No. 172, BRT vs. ICRR in re Crew Consist, December 1968 Conference and Negotiations Following Report of EB 172, 1968-1969 (Box 19, Folder 2k)
  - Emergency Board No. 172, BRT vs. ICRR in re Crew Consist, Negotiations Following Report of EB 172, 1969 (Box 19, Folder 2l)
  - Emergency Board No. 172, BRT vs. ICRR in re Crew Consist, Negotiations Following Report of EB 172, 1967-1969 (Box 19, Folder 2m)
  - Emergency Board No. 172, BRT vs. ICRR in re Crew Consist. Efficiency Study and Statistics, 1967-1969 (Box 19, Folder 2n)
  - Emergency Board No. 172, BRT vs. ICRR in re Crew Consist, Time and Motion Study (Back-Up Material), 1967-1969 (Box 19, Folder 2o)
  - Emergency Board No. 172, BRT vs. ICRR in re Crew Consist, Time and Motion Study (Back-Up Material), 1967-1969 (Box 19, Folder 2p)
  - Emergency Board No. 172, BRT vs. ICRR in re Crew Consist, Time and Motion Study (Back-Up Material), 1967-1969 (Box 19, Folder 2q)
  - Emergency Board No. 172, BRT vs. ICRR in re Crew Consist, Miscellaneous Data Sheets, 1967-1969 (Box 19, Folder 2r)
  - Emergency Board No. 172, BRT vs. ICRR in re Crew Consist, Miscellaneous Data Sheets, 1967-1969 (Box 19, Folder 2s)
  - Correspondence regarding BLE request for second engineer on diesel engines [folder 1 of 3], 1949-1957 (Box 20, Folder 1a)
    Engineers and Firemen: manning of electric and diesel engines, request for second engineer. Volume I, closed December 1957.
  - Correspondence regarding BLE request for second engineer on diesel engines [folder 2 of 3], 1949-1957 (Box 20, Folder 1b)
  - Correspondence regarding BLE request for second engineer on diesel engines [folder 3 of 3], 1949-1957 (Box 20, Folder 1c)
  - Arbitration Re: Illinois Central and Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen Special Board of Adjustment Number 3, Chicago, St. Louis, Mississippi Divisions, and Mayfield and Louisville Districts of Kentucky Division, 1965 (Box 20, Folder 2a)
  - Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen Summary, Miss., St. Louis, Illinois and Chicago Divisions, and Mayfield and Louisville Districts of Kentucky Division, 1964- 1965 (Box 20, Folder 2b)
  - Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen Reply to Volume 1, General, 1964-1965 (Box 20, Folder 2c)
  - Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen Reply to Volume 2, Iowa Division, 1964-1965 (Box 20, Folder 2d)
  - Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen Reply to Volume 3 - Part I and Part II, Chicago Division, 1964-1965 (Box 20, Folder 2e)
  - Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen Reply to Volume 4, Kentucky Division, 1964-1965 (Box 20, Folder 2f)
  - Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen Reply to Volume 5, Illinois Division, 1964-1965 (Box 20, Folder 2g)
  - Arbitration Re: Illinois Central and Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen, Special Board of Adjustment Number 1, Iowa and Kentucky Divisions, 1964 (Box 20, Folder 2h)
  - Arbitration Re: Illinois Central Railroad and Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen, Special Board of Adjustment Number 2, Memphis and Tennessee Divisions, 1964 (Box 20, Folder 2i)
  - Arbitration Re: Illinois Central Railroad and Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen, Louisiana Division (Volume 1), 1964 (Box 20, Folder 2j)
  - Arbitration Re: Illinois Central Railroad and Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen, Louisiana Division (Volume 2), 1964 (Box 20, Folder 2k)
  - Arbitration Re: Illinois Central Railroad and Brotherhood of Railroad Division, Louisiana Division (Volume 3), 1964 (Box 20, Folder 2l)
  - Pay Structure Study for Railroad Operating Employees, National Railway Labor Conference [folder 1 of 2], 1969 (Box 21, Folder 1a)
  - Pay Structure Study for Railroad Operating Employees, Supplemental Appendix Material, National Railway Labor Conference [folder 2 of 2], 1969 (Box 21, Folder 1b)
  - Excessive proportion - Aged employees, single class of employees, 1967 (Box 21, Folder 2)
    By Class and Location
  - Deletions from Active Service by Employees Class Number, 1966 (Box 21, Folder 3a)
  - Report on Quits: Attrition reports, 1966 (Box 21, Folder 3b)
- Series Series 5: Miscellaneous, 1934-1954
  Miscellaneous pamphlets and correspondence
  - Miscellaneous pamphlets, 1935-1949 (Box 21, Folder 4)
    Miscellaneous pamphlets unattached to any files
    - Item 1: Settlements Made by Vice President W. M. Dolan Whiles Assigned to Illinois Central Committee, 1944-1947, 1949; Pamphlet (Box 21, Folder 4)
      Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen, General Grievance Committee, Illinois Central System, Chicago 37, Illinois. Accomplishments of the General Grievance Committee with the assistance of Vice Presidents since the re-organization of 1944.
      Format: Pamphlet.
    - Item 2: Wanted - Improved Labor Leadership, 1935; Pamphlet (Box 21, Folder 4)
      "Should unions be compelled to accept legal and financial responsibility?" Compliments of Lexington Avenue Civic Assoc., Inc. by William D. Rawlins
    - Item 3: Progress in Labor Relations, 1935; Pamphlet (Box 21, Folder 4)
      An address by Frank Purnell, president, The Youngstown Sheet and Tube Company, at the forty-fourth general meeting of the American Iron & Steel Institute
    - Item 4: Labor Relations in the Steel Industry, 1936; Pamphlet (Box 21, Folder 4)
      An address by Charles R. Hook, president, The American Rolling Mill Company, at the forty-fifth meeting of the American Iron & Steel Institute.
    - Item 5: The Long and Short of It: On train length laws, 1937; Pamphlet (Box 21, Folder 4)
      by the Transportation Association of America
    - Item 6: Retail Prices, June 1937, 1936; Pamphlet (Box 21, Folder 4)
      U.S. Department of Labor. Prepared by Retail Price Division and Cost od Living Division.
  - Miscellaneous, 1935-1954 (Box 21, Folder 5)
    Two unrelated letters that have become detached from their files (1935, 1954).